It's no use.
Shikamaru, you must come
to your senses.
(サイ)ムダだよ シカマル。
キミも目覚めるんだ。
Forget it!
I hate to be woken up when
I'm having a good sleep!
(シカマル)冗談じゃねえ！
俺はな 気持よく寝てるとこを
起こされるのが→
大嫌いなんだよ！
kara no kokoro wo terasu mono wa nani?
What brightens up an empty heart?
sakebi tsuzukeru hikari todoku made
I will keep on singing until the light reaches you
falling through the cracks kurayami e ochiteku
Falling through the cracks, Falling into the darkness
anata no sono te o zettai hanasanai
I will never let go of your hand
tell me the story of your life mada michi no tochuu
Tell me the story of your life, We're still on our way
anata o watashi wa zettai akiramenai
I will never give up on you
osaerarenai shoudou nanigenai hibi wa aijyou
Urges I can't suppress, I live for the ordinary days
natsukashii kaze ni furimukeba itsud
When I turn my cheek to a nostalgic wind
emo anata no koe ga suru yo
I always hear your voice
underdog wa wander around
Underdog will Wander around
mawari michi shitemo nigeru yori mashi yo
Even if I take the long way around,
it's better than running away
jibun de jibun o shinjirare nakucha dare wo shinjiru no?
If I can't learn to believe in myself,
then who can I believe in?
hikari ni sono te kazase
Hold up your hand to the light
shining through the clouds kurayami e ochiteku
Shining through the clouds, Falling into the darkness
anata no sono te o zettai hanasanai
I will never let go of your hand
tell me what is on your mind hateshinai yume wo
Tell me what is on your mind,
Chasing the never ending dream
oikake bokura wa zettai akiramenai
We will never give up
kotae no nai jinsei ni kujike sou ni naru kedo
Discouraged by a life without answers, but I...
don’t give it up! keep it up! turn it upside down!
Don't give it up! Keep it up! Turn it upside down!
kokoro wa tsunagatteru yo tatoe tooku hanaretemo
Our hearts will always be connected,
no matter how far apart we may be
tomo ni tomo ni ikiteyukou
Let's share this life together
Cloud of Suspicion
ハァ。
Silver-4c, pawn-3f, rook-4b, rook-4h,
(シカマル)４三銀 ３六歩 ４二飛→
bishop-3f, pawn-1f, pawn-1d,
pawn-2f, king-6b...
４八飛 ３六角 １六歩→
１四歩 ２六歩 ６二玉→
King-6h, king-7b, king-7h, silver-6b...
６八玉 ７二玉→
７八玉 ６二銀。
You're really hanging in there.
(サイ)ずいぶん頑張るじゃないか。
The average shinobi would
have given up long ago.
並みの忍なら とっくに
音を上げているところだよ。
I'm busy playing shogi
with past masters.
I don't have time to get bored.
歴代の名人たちとの対局に
忙しくてね。
I like your stubbornness.
退屈してる暇なんてねえ。
You can learn a lot from shogi.
好きだな キミのそういう強がり。
No matter what position you're in,
there's always a way out.
将棋から学ぶことは多いぞ。
どんな局面にも必ず
逆転の筋が残されているしな。
Are you planning on
getting out of this situation?
I look forward to seeing that.
この状況から逆転する気かい？
それは楽しみだ。
Hey, can you at least
give me back my lighter?
なぁ ライターだけでも返してくれよ。
I just can't calm down
without it.
Sure, when you decide to
accept Lord Gengo's beliefs.
あれがねえと落ち着かねえんだ。
シカマルが ゲンゴ様の志を
受け入れる気になったらね。
Why would you follow
a guy like that?
Let's just say I found
the place where I belong.
どうして あんなやつに従うんだ？
And that wasn't
the Hidden Leaf Village?
僕はただ
自分の居場所を見つけただけさ。
Weren't you a member of Team 7?
木ノ葉は違うってのか？
Then why didn't Naruto come?
お前は第七班の
一員じゃなかったのかよ？
You and I aren't close,
so why did you come?
だったら どうしてナルトが来ない？
それほど親しくもなかった
キミが来たのは なぜなんだろうね？
Naruto knows nothing
about this situation.
今回の一件
ナルトは何も聞かされちゃいねえ。
This was all my decision.
Even still, if this had been
Sasuke or Sakura,
全部 俺の判断だ。
surely Naruto would have come...
だとしても
もしこれが サスケやサクラだったら→
I bet Gengo put those ideas
in your head, right?
ナルトが来たんじゃないのかな？
どうせ その考えも
ゲンゴに吹き込まれたんだろ？
There's no doubt that
Gengo controls people with words.
ゲンゴが言葉で人を操ってるのは
間違いねえ。
So why don't you snap out
of it and wake up?
I woke up a long time ago.
お前も いいかげん目を覚ませ。
When Lord Gengo gave me a will.
目なら とっくに覚めてるよ。
ゲンゴ様に志をいただいたときにね。
Wait.
フッ…。
Do you still have more to say?
I promise...
待てよ。
まだ何か？
I'm gonna undo Gengo's jutsu
and save you.
必ず ゲンゴの術を見破って
お前を助けてやるからな。
I'd resign myself if I were you.
そろそろ観念したほうがいい。
Otherwise, things will get much worse.
でないと
もっと ひどいことになるよ。
You're a member of the Hidden Leaf.
Don't forget that!
(シカマル)お前は木ノ葉の一員だ。
それを忘れんな！
Pawn-4e, bishop-3c...
４五歩 ３三角 ３七桂…。
Knight-3g...
Nope...
I don't have enough pieces right now.
The king's gonna get away.
ダメだ
今の手持ちじゃ駒が足りねえ。
玉に逃げられちまう。
Ro! Is that you?!
That voice... is it you Lord Shikamaru?
朧 お前か!?
Hey Gengo!
(朧)その声は シカマル殿でござるか？
These guys were just
obeying my orders!
おいゲンゴ こいつらは
俺の命令で動いてただけだ。
If you're gonna kill someone,
kill me!
Remember, as long as you live,
there's a chance.
やるなら俺だけにしろ。
(朧)うぅ…。
Don't give up!
(シカマル)いいか 生きてりゃ
機は必ず来る。
I won't let you give up and die!
諦めるんじゃねえぞ。
くたばりやがったら
承知しねえからな！
Worry not.
This is nothing...
(朧)だ… 大丈夫でござる。
このくらい屁のカッパでござるよ。
What happened to Soku?
Wasn't she with you?
She's okay, isn't she?!
(シカマル)鏃はどうした？
一緒じゃねえのか？
あいつも無事なんだろ!?
Why do you insist on
serving Feudal Lords
(鏃)あ！
(ゲンゴ)なぜ大名や無能な民どもに
虐げられながら→
and incompetent people
who oppress you?
Like, that's none of
your business!
それでもなお
やつらのために尽くすのだ？
Remember...
(鏃)お前には関係ないし。
The way that those people
looked at you.
(ゲンゴ)思い出せ
お前を見る民どもの目を。
What did you see deep
inside their eyes?
Like, I don't remember!
その奥には何が見えた？
Sure, you do.
(鏃)そんなの 忘れたし。
The truth is, it's stuck to your mind
and won't go away. Isn't that so?
(ゲンゴ)そんなはずはない。
本当は頭にこびりついて
離れないのだろう？
Remember!
The eyes that looked at you.
思い出せ
お前を見る やつらの目を。
The suspicious eyes
that feared me,
and tried to discriminate against me...
あれは私を恐れ 疑い
遠ざけようとする目。
Why must you give your proud and
mighty life for people like that?
(ゲンゴ)そんな
下賤の者どものために→
Why pledge loyalty to those
who hold you in bondage?
なにゆえ誇り高きお前が
命をかけねばならぬ？
なにゆえ
お前を縛る者のために➡
They are using me.
忠義を尽くさねばならぬのだ？
(鏃)あいつらは 私を利用する…。
Everyone is an enemy.
There is nothing to fear.
みんな敵だ。
Now, turn.
And accept everything.
(ゲンゴ)恐れることはない。
振り向け。
すべてを受け入れるのだ。
A will has just been granted.
(鏃)うわぁ～！
今 ここに
志は 授けられた。
I've brought him, Lord Gengo...
(サイ)連れてまいりました ゲンゴ様。
My apologies for
the inhospitable treatment.
窮屈な思いをさせて すまない。
As you know,
I can't let down my guard.
I have no intention
of speaking to you.
用心を怠るわけには
いかないのでね。
It's obvious you're trying
to control me with your words.
てめえと話す気はねえ。
You're starting to look
like your father.
言葉で操ろうって魂胆が
見え見えだぜ。
お父上の面影に
似てきたのではないか？
Forgive me, but I looked
into your background.
Your family and friends...
悪いが 調べさせてもらったよ。
ご家族や友人のこと。
And the fact that
you came here to kill me.
それに貴君が
私を殺しに来たこともね。
Why do you people
keep oppressing us?
When did we do that?
貴君らは なぜ我々を虐げるのだ？
This land is feeble.
俺たちが いつ虐げた？
We barely have natural resources
and the ground is fallow,
この国は弱い。
満足な資源もなく→
yet we are trying
our hardest to survive. That is all.
作物も育たぬ不毛の地で→
Yeah right, all the while
you're gathering up Rogue Ninja...
ただ必死に
生きのびようとしているだけだ。
What's your motive?
(シカマル)抜け忍をかき集めといて
よく言うぜ！
Are you planning on starting a war?
I'm not gathering them.
目的は何だ？
戦争でも始めようってのか？
They come to me,
seeking salvation.
集めているのではない。
彼らのほうから救いを求めて
集まってくるのだ。
Salvation?!
Have you never questioned
the current existence of shinobi?
救いだと？
貴君は今の忍のあり方に
疑問を持ったことはないか？
Without war,
they are no more than hunting dogs
for Feudal Lords and the rich.
戦もせず 大名や金持ちどもの
走狗に甘んじる。
Is that truly a fitting life
for a shinobi?
What is it that
you're trying to say?
それで真の忍といえるだろうか？
They come here because
they want to be real shinobi.
何が言いてえ？
この国に集まってくる者たちは→
皆 忍らしくありたいと
願っているだけだ。
The alliance of nations
to maintain a dark peace...
and bind shinobi with
meaningless laws.
連合は やみくもに
平和を求めるあまり→
But there will always
be those who reject it.
忍を無意味な掟で縛るばかり。
This land is merely
the gathering place for them.
だが そこから
はみ出す人間は必ず出てくる。
この国は その受け皿に
なっているにすぎぬ！
Various rules are necessary
to preserve peace.
平和を維持するためには
多少のルールは必要だ！
The peace you speak of
is nothing but a theory,
forced upon us
by the Great Nations.
貴君のいう平和とは
すべて 大国が押し付ける理屈だ。
The Tailed Beasts that
you keep are proof of that.
その証拠に貴君らは
尾獣を有している。
Had you used one,
this land would be
completely helpless.
もしも あれを使われたら
この国など ひとたまりもない。
Isn't that so?
We have no intention of ever using
a Tailed Beast for war again.
違うかね？
俺たちは 二度と 尾獣を
戦に使うつもりなんかねえ。
You keep the Tailed Beast
to yourselves,
and you expect us to believe that?
自分たちだけ
尾獣を所有しておいて→
Isn't that the biggest excuse
by the Great Nations?
我々に その言葉を
信じろというのか？
Quit jumping to conclusions.
それが大国の理屈でなくて
なんなのだ？
Then how about this?
勝手に決めてんじゃねえよ！
ならば どうだ？
Give this land a Tailed Beast too.
この国にも尾獣をくれぬか？
I'm sure the Hidden Cloud
has an extra one, correct?
たしか雲隠れの里に
一匹残っていたな。
Then we wouldn't worry,
and we would believe you.
そうすれば 我々も安心して
貴君らのことを信じよう。
You know we can't do that.
Of course not.
んなこと できっこねえだろ！
そうだろうとも。
You espouse peace openly...
but deep down, you don't trust
small countries like ours.
口先では平和を唱えながら
結局のところ貴君らは→
我々のような小国のことなど
信用していないのだからな！
But you can't make the argument
for war because of that.
だからって戦をしていいっていう
理屈にはならねえ！
There's got to be another solution.
他にも解決策はあるはずだ！
You need another solution?
Come with me.
他の解決策か…。
I'd like to show you something...
来たまえ。
貴君に見せたいものがある。
What is this?
Agricultural crops can't grow
at our elevation.
ここは…。
標高の高い この里では
作物も ろくに育たない。
The people live in poverty
with little to eat.
人々の生活の糧はなく
貧しさに あえぐばかりだ。
If we just had some kind
of product,
something to add value
to their lives...
せめて 何か物産品があれば
生活の足しになる。
This flower is the result
of selective breeding.
そう考えて
品種改良で作ったのが この花だ。
You've seen it here and there,
haven't you?
貴君も あちこちで
目にしたのではないかな？
But it was all for nothing...
This flower wilts the moment
it's taken out of this village,
しかし ムダだったよ。
due to its unique environment.
この花は 里から出したとたんに
枯れてしまう。
Why did you choose
the way of the shinobi?
この里の環境は特殊なのだ。
貴君は どうして
忍の道を目指した？
Was it to file away documents
for the rest of your life?
Who knows.
書類整理をするためか？
さぁな。
Most likely not.
You train daily to hone
your skills.
おそらくは違うはずだ。
日々 忍の腕を磨き
己を鍛え上げる。
And with your skills,
you defeat the enemy,
to protect what is precious.
そして その技をもって 敵を倒し
大切なものを守る。
That is the way a shinobi
should live.
That is the way your father
and mentor lived.
それこそが忍らしい生き方だ。
かつて お父上や恩師が
そうしたようにな。
How would you know?!
You probably hope that you can
measure up to them someday.
てめえに 何がわかる！
貴君とて いずれ 彼らに
肩を並べたいと思わぬはずがない。
But in a world of peace,
can you really accomplish that?
しかし
ただ平和なだけの世の中で→
果たして それが
成し得るだろうか？
It is because of war,
戦があったからこそ 忍の技術は
めざましい発展を遂げたのだ。
that shinobi abilities underwent
remarkable development.
If there had been continual peace,
even you would never have spent
such worthwhile moments with your friends.
もし 平和が続いていたら→
今の貴君も
友と過ごした価値ある時間も→
Am I wrong?
すべて 得られなかったはずだ。
違うかね？
If that's the price for peace,
I'll gladly throw down my weapons.
それが 平和の代償なら
俺は喜んで 武器を置く！
You're not speaking
from your heart.
You feel your own abilities
weakening, don't you?
それは本心ではない。
(シカマルの声)お前自身 腕の衰えを
感じているんだろう？
Shikamaru...
Shut up!
シカマル君。
Stay out of this.
その口を閉じろ！
Do not fear, Shikamaru.
手を出すな。
恐れることはない シカマルよ。
Put your hand down.
さぁ その手を下ろしなさい。
Yes, that's it.
First, why don't you calm down?
そうだ それでいい。
Take a deep breath.
まずは 落ち着こうじゃないか。
深呼吸してみたまえ。
Do you like it?
The scent of my precious flowers?
どうだね？
私の自慢の花の香りは。
Come on.
I get it...
So, that's it.
さぁ。
なるほど… そういうわけか。
The scent of certain flowers has
the effect of stirring up memories.
ある種の花の香りには
思い出を呼び覚ます薬効がある。
So, that's what you've been
using to brainwash people.
てめえは それを
洗脳に利用したってわけだ。
What inconceivable will...
But that discovery won't
get you anywhere.
とんだ志だぜ！
それに気づいたところで
どうにもなるまい。
You cannot disobey me.
Where are my comrades?!
Where are Ro and Soku?!
私に逆らうことなどできぬ。
Bring them here!
俺の仲間は… 朧と鏃は どこだ!?
We are right here.
ここへ連れてこい！
Huh?! You two?!
(朧)もう来ているでござる。
あぁっ！ お前ら!!
Like, Lord Gengo has
given us the will...
(鏃)私たちは
ゲンゴ様に志をいただいたんだし。
Find him! Don't let him escape
from this castle!
捜せ！ やつをこの城から出すな!!
Shikamaru, it's useless to hide.
シカマル… 隠れても ムダだよ。
I'm still numb...
Damn it, Soku!
うぅ… まだ痺れてやがる。
鏃のやつめ！
I can't use my Shadows.
My rook and bishop two-piece
handicap is gone too.
The situation is bleak.
影は使えねえ。 飛車角も取られた。
状況は かんばしくねえな…。
It's unlike you...
I can't believe you'd go
with the Climbing Silver.
It's using an advance unit
to break through enemy lines.
((シカマル : 珍しいっすね
いきなり棒銀なんて。
You have to be ready to use tactics
like this once in a while...
(アスマ)敵陣突破の先兵だ。
(たまには
こういう指し方もできねえとな))
If I escape now, the risk for
the Hidden Leaf will increase.
That's what you told me back then.
ここで逃げたら
木ノ葉のリスクが高まる…。
So, I guess that time
has come for me.
あんた あんとき そう言ったよな。
俺にも
そのときが来たってことなのか。
Calm down.
There's still a chance
an opportunity will present itself.
落ち着け。 まだ
逆転の筋は残されてるはずだ。
Shikamaru, presently,
you are the knight.
((アスマ : シカマル…
さしずめ お前は桂馬だな))
Breaking through the enemy camp
with a Climbing Silver or...
敵陣突破の棒銀か
それとも 桂馬の高跳びか。
perhaps a knight that jumps high...
Guess I have no choice
but to jump back into
the den of the king.
ここは もういっぺん
玉の懐に飛び込むしかねえか。
Lord Gengo, are you sure
it's all right
to leave the search
for Shikamaru to Sai?
(朧)ゲンゴ様…
シカマル捜しを サイ殿に任せきりで→
Like, it will be bad if
he gets out of the castle.
よろしいのでござるか？
Don't panic.
(鏃)城の外に逃げられたら
面倒だし。
If he gets cornered,
he's the type
(ゲンゴ)慌てるな。
to throw himself into an even
more difficult situation.
彼は追い込まれれば
追い込まれるほど→
あえて 困難な状況に身を投じる…
そういう男だ。
Isn't that right, Shikamaru?
そうだな？ シカマル。
You knew I was here?
That's no fun.
気づいてたのかよ
つまんねえな。
You wouldn't leave this behind.
貴君が これを
残していくはずはないしな。
You came back just for that?
You're something.
わざわざ戻ってくるなんて
おめでたいやつだし。
Resign yourself
and be captured!
おとなしく捕まるでござる！
If the floor won't work,
there's always the ceiling.
床がダメなら
天井って手もあるんだぜ！
Below.
(朧)下でござる！
My body...
Whoa...
うっ 体が…。
Lord Shikamaru, release me!
おっと！
シカマル殿 はなすでござる！
To break a genjutsu,
the theory is to bring down
the one who placed it.
幻術を解くには
かけた人間を倒すのがセオリーだが→
What do you say, Gengo?
Impossible.
No one can resist my words.
そこんとこは どうなんだ ゲンゴ？
ムダだ 私の言葉に
抗うことなどできぬ。
Ro...
Sorry, but you'll have to
be my shield for a while.
朧 悪いが しばらく
俺の盾になってもらうぜ。
Shoot.
Don't worry about hitting Ro.
Go ahead and shoot.
撃て！
朧に当たっても構わぬ。
Just make sure you aim straight.
撃ってみな
ただし よく狙ってな。
Stop, Shikamaru.
You cannot resist my voice.
シカマル 止まれ！
私の声には逆らえぬ！
Don't tell me you—?!
You purposely let Soku
hit you in the ear
キサマ まさか…。
to dull your sense of hearing?!
鏃の攻撃を
わざと耳に受け→
This is the knight's jump!
一時的に聴覚を麻痺させたのか？
これが桂馬の高跳びだ！
I'm disappointed, Shikamaru.
うわ！
So disappointed.
惜しいな シカマル。
実に惜しい。
Please stay back, Lord Gengo.
Leave this to me.
ゲンゴ様は奥へ。
ここは私にお任せください。
Well done!
Gengo!
よくやった。
(シカマル)ゲンゴ！
You won't get away!
逃がしはせぬ！
Damn it!
しまった！
Damn it, you keep
getting beaten up by girls.
((シカク : ったく てめえは女の子に
やられてばかりだな。
Weren't you going to
become a better leader
for the sake of your comrades?
仲間のため てめえがより優秀に
なるんじゃなかったのかよ？
Dad... I...
I'm just not cut out to
be a shinobi.
(シカマル)親父 俺はさ
やっぱ忍には向いてねえんだよ。
(はあ…))
Is he dead?
I didn't like, kill him yet.
(朧)死んだでござるか？
Well, he had no chance
at the end.
(鏃)まだ殺してはいないし。
How pitiful...
まあ 最後は
やぶれかぶれでござったな。
I'm physically at my limit.
(サイ)哀れなものだね。
The air feels so heavy.
《体も限界だ
空気もやけに重いぜ。
Man, this is such a drag.
なんかもう めんどくせえ》
Are you okay, Shikamaru?
Don't you dare die on us!
(チョウジ)シカマル 大丈夫？
(いの)死んだら
承知しないからね？
ヒヒヒ。
ウフ。
You guys?!
But what're you doing here?
お前ら… っつか
どうしてここに？
Oh, I get it. I'm still dreaming...
Shikamaru!
そっか 俺は まだ夢を…。
T-Temari?!
I expect a lot more from you!
(テマリ)シカマル！
テ テマリ！
Why're you just sitting around
dazed like that?!
お前は 私が見込んだ男だろう？
Shikamaru?!
何ボサッとしてんだよ！
Stop it, Temari!
He'll really die.
シカマル！
やめてよ テマリ！
Shut up!
That's for lying to me at
the Allied Forces meeting.
本当に死んじゃうってば。
黙ってろ！
今のは 連合の会議で
私にウソをついた分だ。
Sorry, Temari.
(シカマル)すまなかったな テマリ。
え？
Thanks to you,
I've come to my senses.
おかげで目が覚めたぜ。
Shikamaru!
Sorry, but can you take over here?
シカマル。
悪いがここ頼めるか？
I have one more guy
to take down.
倒さなきゃならない相手が
もう１人いるんだ。
Is that Gengo?!
How did you know?
ゲンゴだろ？
Lord Hokage told me.
どうして それを？
火影様に聞いたんだ。
I had a hell of a time trying
to get it out of him.
I don't want to
even imagine what you did.
聞き出すのには
ちょっと苦労したけどね。
どうやって聞き出したかは
あんまし想像したくねえな。
So, Shikamaru, it's okay
to crush these guys?
They're brainwashed,
but they're comrades.
シカマル こいつら
倒しちゃっていいんだよね？
Please wake them up as well!
洗脳されてはいるが
２人とも仲間だ。
Like, shut your mouth.
そいつらも
目を覚まさせてやってくれ。
Wait!
You're forgetting one thing.
言ってくれるし！
待て！
え？
もう１つ 忘れ物だぞ！
He probably knows you're coming
and has laid traps.
向こうも
お前が来るのを見越して➡
I hope the odds of your winning
in that condition is good.
罠を張っているはずだ。
I have no intention of being
a sacrificial pawn.
その体で勝算はあるんだろうな？
捨て駒になるつもりはねえ。
All right then!
なら よし！
Okay, let's get on with our final moves...
さて サシの勝負といこうか。
Gengo!
ゲンゴ！
TO BE CONTINUED
kakaeta omou i tokitoshite
Sometimes, the feelings we have
kazoe kirenai itami o
Cause us immense pain
yuzurenai hokori mune ni
We've lived this entire time
imamade ikite kitadarou
With unshakeable pride in our hearts
tatakau koto de mamotte
Defending by fighting
omoigakenaku nakushite
With unexpected losses
kizutsukiai ma nande
We learn as we hurt one another
taisetsu na koto ni kizukudarou
Will we realize what's most important?
koe ga todokanai
My voice cannot reach you
soredemo (soredemo)
Even so
kokoro shinjite iyou
Let's trust our hearts
zenshin zenrei kimi wo mamoru yo
I will protect you with every essence of my being
towa ni sou towa ni
For all eternity
nankaidatte tachiagare yo
Stand up again and again
sono ishi de (sono ishi de)
By your own volition
ungai souten asu wo egaku yo
Don't give in; create a new day
tomo ni sou tomo ni
Together with friends
itsudatte akirameru
Never ever give up
na michi wo hirakou
Let's open up the path
ruru
On and on
Next Episode
The Hidden Leaf still holds that much importance to you?
Damn right!
Then I'll let you in on something good...
What would you think if I said I've sent my comrades
with the will I bestowed upon them, into all of the Hidden Villages?
What did you say?
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Shikamaru's Story, A Cloud Drifting in the Silent Dark, Part 5: Dawn"
Dawn
You don't have the means to stop it!
Tune in again!